Louise Varèse Papers, 1910-1983
Sophia Smith Collection
Louise Varèse Papers
1910-1983
Varèse, Louise, 1890-
MS 167
15 boxes (10 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Biographer and translator. Personal and professional correspondence; photographs; writings; published and unpublished translations of reviews, manuscripts, correspondence, and printed material; research notes; and memorabilia. Material related to Edgard Varèse includes research notes, proofs, manuscripts, and reviews for the Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary; and programs and memorabilia related to his work. Notable correspondents include Edgard Varèse, Jacques Barzun, and Anais Nin.
Biographical Note
Louise Varèse was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, November 20, 1890, daughter of John Lindsay McCutcheon and Mary Louise Taylor. She attended Smith College (class of 1912), leaving in the fall of 1911 to marry Allen Norton. A son, Michael, was born in 1912. She was separated from Norton in 1916, and they were divorced in 1920. In 1922 she married composer Edgard Varèse, throughout her life she translated works of French authors and poets into English, including Rimbaud, Proust, Sartre, Stendahl, and Simenon, among many others and was awarded Chevalier de L'Ordre des Arts et des Lettres by the Republic of France in 1969. She also wrote articles, stories, and poems. Following the death of Edgard Varèse in 1965, she published Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary, Volume I, 1893-1928 in 1972. Volume 2 was in progress when she died July 1, 1989.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Louise Varèse Papers consist of correspondence, photographs, writings, printed materials, research notes, and memorabilia. There is a large amount of correspondence, both personal and professional. It includes correspondence with her friend Maryette Charlton (1971-83), to Edgard Varèse (n.d.), from her son Michael Norton and daughter Sylvia (1930-74), regarding the death of Edgard Varèse (1965), and with various well known art and literary people including Jacques Barzun (1965-73) and Anais Nin (1963-71). There is also professional correspondence regarding music, museums, publishing, and Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary. Also contained in the papers is material related to Louise Varèse's published and unpublished translations: reviews, manuscripts, correspondence, and printed materials. There is also material related to Edgard Varèse; research notes, proofs, manuscripts for both Volume 1 and 2 of Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary, as well as reviews of Volume 1; and programs and memorabilia related to his work. Maryette Charlton collected and added much of the material related to Varèse, including two tape recordings, photographs, biographical chronologies, and memorabilia.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized as follows:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
II. CORRESPONDENCE
III. WRITINGS
IV. MEMORABILIA
V. BOOKS AND PERIODICALS [on shelf]
SERIES VI. PERIODICALS
ADDITIONS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The Papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
The Louise Varèse Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1975 to 1987 by Louise Varèse and Maryette Charlton.
Barzun, Jacques, 1907- --Correspondence; Nin, Anaïs, 1903-1977--Correspondence; Varèse, Louise, 1890-; Varèse, Edgard, 1883-1965; Musicians--United States--Biography--Sources; Translators--United States--Biography--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Varèse, Louise, 1890-. Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary -- Sources
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS
  - Genealogy (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - L.V. Notes kept by Maryette about L.V. - biographical (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - List of names with person's relation to Edgar Varèse taken from Varése, by Louise Varèse, New York, WW Norton 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs
    - 1913-1970s (Box 1, Folder 4-10)
    - Family (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - LV with Jeanne de Lanux and photo by Esta V. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Edgar Varèse (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Allen Norton (1st husband) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cartoon of LV by Edgard V (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Poem "To Louise Varese" by Mungo Park 1902(?) (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Red Book - diary (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notebook [LV] (Box 1, Folder 19)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - From Louise Varèse
    - B (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cavallo, Diana n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Charlton, Mayette 1971-74 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Lieberman, Mr.n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Vivier, Odilen.d. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - To Louise Varèse
    - A (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Alcaraz, Jose Antonio (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Alcopley, Nina and Una Dora (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Aldan, Daisy (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Aimengaud, Marie Elizabeth (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - B (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Beach, Sylvia (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Barzun, Jacques (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Block, David (Box 3, Folder 8a)
    - Bouchard, Diane and Thomas (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Boulez, Pierre (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - C (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Calder, Sandy (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Cavallo, Diana (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Charbonnier, Georges (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Charlton, Maryette-1971-74 (Box 3, Folder 15-17)
    - Claude, Albert (Nobel prize for The Cell) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - D (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Dombek, Blanche (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Dorbon, Lucien - Fr. Dere (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Duchamp, Marcel and Teeny (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Duenas, Ricardo T. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - E (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Elman, Richard (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - F (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Felton, James (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Ficke, Arthur Davison (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - G (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Garland-Soundings, Peter (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Geist, Stanley (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Gibbs, Margaret (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Gilder, Rodman (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Gordon, Witold (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Green, Hannah (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Guerard, Albert J. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - H (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Henderson, Carol (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hirbour-Coron, Lucie (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ito, Migo (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - J (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - olivet, H & A (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - K (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Kerr, Harrison (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Kiesler, Lillian (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Kolb, Barbara (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Kousseritsky, Olga - Mme. Serge Kousseitsky (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - L (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Ladany, Dr. Imre (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Lederman, Minna (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - de Lanux, Jeanne and Eyre (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Levin, Harry (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Lewis, Francis (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Lucius, Florence (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - M (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - McMillan, Ann (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Masters, Edgar Lee (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - MIRO (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous items received in correspondence (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - N (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Nin, Anais (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Norton, Michael (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Ouellette, Fernand (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - P (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Padma (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Parks, Anna (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Pierce, Ellen and John (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Puccinelli, Raymond (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - R (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Rathsman, Siri (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Robert, Olga (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - S (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sanouillet, Michael (Box 5, Folder 1a)
    - Shearer, John (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - T (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Tabatoni, Pierre - Ambassade de France (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Thompson, Virgin (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Tully, Alice (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - U (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Varèse-Mulder, Claude (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Vivier, Odile (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - W (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Watts, Chi and Schuyler (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Wergel, Henriette (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Weinberg, Diane Cavalle (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - We Chung, Chou (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Winslow, Kirk (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Yates, Peter (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Z (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - To LV following death of Edgard
    - Telegrams / Cables (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Publishers (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Universities (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - MacDowell Colony and American Academy of Poets (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Composers' organizations, Will Shuster, Museum of Irish Art (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Bank of NY, US, and French governments (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - A - C (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - D - K (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - L - M (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - N - R (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - S - V (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - W - Z (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Re: Music, museums, publishing, translations, and Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary
    - Authors
      - Fowlie, Wallace 1945-52 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Grace, Julien 1947 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Leger, Alexis (St John Perse) 1941-56 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Michaeux, Henri 1957-63 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Poets, Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Simeon, Georges (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Banks and USIA (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Museums
      - Arts Council of Great Britain (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Haifa, Music Museum and Library (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Musee National D"Art Moderne (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Museum of Modern Art (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Philadelphia Museum of Art (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Music
      - Arts Council of Great Britain (Box 7, Folder 13)
      - Columbia University Department of Music (Box 7, Folder 14)
      - Bartok Archivuum (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Communications industries (Box 7, Folder 16)
      - Eastman School of Music (Box 7, Folder 17)
      - Ensemble Instrumental de Musique Contemp de Paris (Box 7, Folder 18)
      - La Foundation Maeght (Box 7, Folder 19)
      - May Fest (Box 7, Folder 20)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 21)
      - The National Theatre (Box 7, Folder 22)
      - New York Philharmonic (Box 7, Folder 23)
      - Semaines Musicales International (Box 7, Folder 24)
      - Utah Symphony Orchestra (Box 7, Folder 25)
      - Universities - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Publishers
      - The Bollingen Series (Box 7, Folder 26)
      - C.F. Peters Corp. (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - City Lights Books (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - McGraw Hill Book Co. (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 30)
      - New Directions (Box 7, Folder 31)
      - New Directions - Contracts (Box 7, Folder 32)
      - New Directions - Royalty Stets. (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - W.W. Norton & CO., LND. (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary - Miscellaneous correspondence to LV (Box 7, Folder 35)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS
  - List of translations (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Early notes/clippings (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - "The Blind Man" and "Buddha of the Bathroom" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Limerick about Varèse in Santa Fe (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "The Little Wax Candle" (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Marcel Duchamp at Play" 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Poetic Art of Photography" (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Pony House" and drawing for Edgard (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Translations
    - Author, Looten, Michaux (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - With the French Author, Sokolova, Nadia (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous - other manuscripts (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Poetry (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Marie the Virgin and the Virgins" Antibes 1927 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Miserable Miracle" (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Slaughter of the Innocents" (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Together Still", Michaux 1948 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Translator's note to Perse's "Eloques and Other Poems" 1956 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - For Nancy Reid program 1947 (soprano) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Translations known to exist but have not been found (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Unpublished (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Unidentified - "The Chess Game" 1916 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Unidentified - "Liminana" Poems 1925 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Unidentified - "The One All Alone" 1927-8 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Unidentified - Stories (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Reviews of Translations
    - "Paris Spleen," Baudelaire (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - "Joy," George Bernanos (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - "Castle of Argol," Gracq, Julien (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Parenthesis," Jacques Lemarchand (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Le Miserable Miracle," Michaux, H. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - St. John Perse (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - "Pleasures and Regrets," Proust (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Rimbaud, Arthur (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Sartre, Jean Paul (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Simenon, George (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Lucien Leuwen," Stendhal (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - New Yorker, "Musical Events - Sound and Spaces" (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Corrected manuscripts
    - Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary, Vol. 1. Part 1. Early Years 1883-1915 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary: Entire manuscript of Vol. 1 only (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary, Vol. I
    - Proofs (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Notes - Vol. II (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Incomplete segment of Vol. II - Back to NY 1933-1937 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Reviews - Varèse; A Looking-Glass Diary (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Recording, exhibition, awards, medals, organizations
    - Transcribed tape - Varèse and Alcopley, Leonardo 1963 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Application for Guggenheim (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Denyse Clairouin Award (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - D'officier Dans l'ordre Des Arts et Des Lettres 1957-1968 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Organizations - P.E.N. (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Organizations - The MacDowell Company (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Duchamp, Marcel - Exhibition of his work - Museum of Modern Art (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Programs
    - To Paris for "Hommages a Varèse" 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - For Edgard Varèse's work performed 1972 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - For Edgard Varèse's work performed 1973-74 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Attended by Louise Varèse (Box 12, Folder 4)
- SERIES IV. MEMORABILIA
  - Louise Varèse's clippings, poems etc collected by her (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Contents list contributed to SSC compiled by Maryette Charlton (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous - cutout (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Flores, Angel - Assignment of copyright (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Menu signed by friends (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Negatives of photographs of LV for Claude Varèse 1972 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Photos of LV by Esta Varèse 1920, 1921 [or 22] (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Edgard Varèse's monogram for LV (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Reception - list of invites - Le Conseiller Culturel (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Rogue II - October (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Rogue II - December (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Souvenir from Igor Kio Mocow Circus (Box 13, Folder 12)
- SERIES V. BOOKS
  - Baudelaire, Charles, Paris Spleen, New Directions, NY (2 copies) 1970
  - Bernanos, Georges, Joy, Pantheon Books, NY 1946
  - Bernstein, Joseph M., ed., Baudelaire Rimbaud Verlaine - Selected Verse and Prose Poems, Citadel Press, NY 1947
  - Breton, Andre, Silence is Golden, Soundings 1973 (2 copies)
  - Brown, Everett, Harrison, Masterworks of World Literature, Third Edition Volume II Shakespeare-Sartre, Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, Inc. 1970
  - Fernandez, Ronald, Social Psychology Through Literature, John Wiley and Sons, NY 1972
  - Geist, Stanley, ed., French Stories and Tales, Alfred A. Knopf, NY 1954
  - Gracq, Julien, The Castle of Argol, Direction, Norfolk, CT 1951
  - Gracq, Julien, The Castle of Argol, Peter Owen Limited,London 1951
  - Gracq, Julien, Au Chateau d'Argol, Jose Corti, Paris
  - Kulik, William T. and Omans, Glen A., Faces of Authority, Scott, Foresman, and Company, Glenview, IL 1972
  - Lipking, Lawrence I. and Litz, A. Walton, ed.
  - Modern Literary Criticism 1900-1970, Athenum, NY, 1972
  - Michaux, Henri, Miserable Miracle, City Lights Book, San Francisco 1963
  - Michaux, Henri, Nous Deux Encore, J. Lambert and Company, Paris 1948
  - Mickiewicz, Adam, The Great Improvisation, Voyages, NY 1956
  - Mills, Clark., ed., Adam Michiewicz - Selected Poems, The Noonday Press, Inc., NY 1956 (2 copies)
  - Perse, St. John, Collected Poems, Princeton University Press, Princeton, NJ 1971
  - Perse, St. John, Eloges and Other Poems, W.W. Norton and Company, NY 1956
  - Perse, St. John, Exile and Other Poems, Pantheon Books, NY 1956
  - Proust, Marcel, Pleasures and Regrets, Crown Publishers, NY 1944
  - Rimbaud, Arthur, Illuminations, New Directions, NY 1947, 2 copies
  - Rimbaud, Arthur, Illuminations, revised edition, New Directions, NY (2 copies) 1957
  - Rimbaud, Arthur, A Season in Hell, New Directions, Norfolk, CT 1952
  - Rimbaud, Arthur, A Season in Hell and The Drunken Boat, New Directions, NY 1961
  - Sartre, Jean-Paul, The Chips Are Down, Lear,, NY 1948
  - Scheaffer, Louis, O'Neill Son and Artist, Little, Brown, and Company, Boston 1973
  - Scheaffer, Louis, O'Neill Son and Playwright, Little, Brown, and Company, Boston 1968
  - Simenon, Georges, Act of Passion, Routledge and Kegan Paul, Ltd., London 1953
  - Simenon, Georges, The Girl in His Past, Prentice-Hall, Inc., NY 1952
  - Simenon, Georges, The Heart of a Man, Prentice-Hall, Inc., NY 1951
  - Simenon, Georges, Maigret, Lognon et Les Gangsters, Presses do la Cite, Paris 1952
  - Simenon, Georges, Satan's Children, Prentice-Hall, Inc., NY 1953
  - Simenon, Georges, The Snow Was Black, Prentice-Hall, Inc., NY 1950
  - Stendhal, The Green Huntsman, New Directions, NY 1950
  - Stendhal, The Telegraph, New Directions, NY 1950
  - Valery, Paul, Selected Writings, New Directions, Binghamton, NY 1950
  - Varèse, Louise, Varèse, Davis-Poynter, Great Britain 1972
  - Varèse, Louise, Varèse, W.W. Norton and Company, Inc., NY 1972 (2 copies)
- SERIES VI. PERIODICALS [on shelf]
  - Arts News Annual, XXVI 1957
  - The Chimera, Vol. II, No. 4 (2 copies)1944
  - The Chimera, Vol. IV, No. 2 (2 copies)1946
  - Evergreen Review ed. by Allen, Donald, and Rosset, Vol. I, No. 1, Grove Press, NY 1957
  - The Paris Review, Paris 1957
  - The Polish Review, Vol. I, No. 2-3 1956
  - Quarterly Review of Literature ed. by Paul Valery, Vol. III, New Haven (2 copies)
  - Retort ed. by Holley R. Cantine, Jr., Vol. II, No. 2 1944
- ADDITIONS (unprocessed)
  - R. KIVE; Presented 8/8/871987
  - Chronology
  - Allen Norton
  - The New Yorker (3) May 13, 1974
  - Louise Varèse Birthday Celebrations
  - Correspondence: Louise Varèse
  - Certificate of Naturalization 1927
  - Correspondence from Louise Varèse to Edgard Varèse, etc.
  - Correspondence to Louise Varèse pre-1975
  - Correspondence to Louise Varèse 1975
  - Correspondence to Louise Varèse 1976-77
  - Correspondence from Louise Varèse to Maryette Charlton 1975- )
  - Correspondence to Maryette Charlton from Sylvia Gillis 1985- ?
  - Reviews of A Looking Glass Diary, Vol. I
  - Rough drafts of Louise Varèse for article "Marcel Duchamp at Play" 1975
  - Two tape recordings of Louise Varèse by Maryette Charlton made on using MC's Nagra, 2/1/721972
  - Louise Varèse "Likes"
  - R. KIVE; Presented 8/8/871987
  - Posters, reviews, relating to "A Varèse Celebration" 1883-1983
  - Louise Varèse activities, relating to Edgard Varèse, concerts, et al.
  - Photographs of Louise Varèse by Brassai, et al (some with negatives, inter. negatives, labeled)
  - Photograph of Allen Norton with negatives
  - Maryette Charlton's Photographs + negatives, color slides
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Newspaper clipping of Louise Varese's obituary 1989
  - Newspaper article featuring Edgard Varese and three other composers
  - Advertisements for "A Varese Celebration - December 1, 1983" and "A Night of Music" 1983, n.d.